Okay, ברוך השם. Baruch Hashem.
Actually Joe’s ninety-first birthday. Oh wow.
Okay, ברוך השם. Baruch Hashem. So today's דף daf is יט. Yud
Tet. We pick up at the bottom of
יח עמוד ב Yud Chet Amud Bet and we start with
איתמר. Itmar. If there's an asterisk next to it, it begins about
twenty lines from the bottom.
The first words on the line are לסדר פורענויות. l’seder puraniot.
Okay, איתמר, Itmar, it was said, it was taught, רב ורבי חנינה,
Rav v’Rabbi Chanina, the debate of רב Rav and רבי חנינה. Rabbi
Chanina. Some have it as רב הונא ורבי חנינה. Rav Huna v'Rabbi
Chanina. אמרי: Amri: בטלה מגילת תענית. Batla Megillat Ta'anit. The scroll of
fasts is annulled. רבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi
Yehoshua Ben Levi אמרי: amri: לא בטלה מגילת תענית. lo Batla Megillat
Ta'anit. The scroll of fasts is not annulled. What is this מגילת
תענית? Megillat Ta'anit? This is actually a very ancient document that dates
from the Second Temple period and it listed all of the dates
in which you do not fast. You're not allowed to fast. All
of the minor festivals that were decreed for the Jewish people, a
lot of them related to things around the Temple or things that
occurred in the חשמונאים Chashmonaim period.
חנוכה Chanukah is listed there as we will see as one of
the things that a days that you do not fast. The days
that you do not fast and you cannot say a הספד, hesped,
you cannot eulogize.
Okay, and it's a really a like I said an ancient book
from Temple period that mentions of historical significance because it gives the
reasons in a very brief half of a sentence: this day because
of X, this day because this happened, this day because that happened.
But it actually
gives some historical facts of things that happened in that period.
It
is interesting that just as jumping forward I guess about a thousand
years, yeah, or more, more than a thousand years forward,
there was you know in the Middle Ages because there were so
many wars between the you know amongst all these various nations the
there was like the Church made like a million of these tiny
little minor holidays, Saints' Days and other holidays and you weren't allowed
to have war on those holidays.
So they managed to like you know try to limit the amount
of days during the year that that the nations could be at
war. But anyway, these are days that you could not fast or
have a תענית. ta'anit. And we actually have a very you know
a manuscripts of not dating back to then but we actually have
the actual מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit as was you know copied
over over hundreds of years in manuscripts. And there's I had meant
to bring in this current scholarly edition, I don't have it, but
there's an excellent new scholarly edition by this woman scholar ורד נעם
Vered Noam in Israel. And in addition to the מגילת תענית, Megillat
Ta'anit, there's a part called the סקוליון, Scholion, the סקוליא, Scolia, which
are like later additions to it and those were written you know
somewhere in the תלמודי Talmudic or post-תלמודי Talmudic period and at times
are like influenced by the גמרא's Gemara interpretation or discussion about it
and you know ours is one example. So it's actually quite interesting
because, this isn't our topic now, was the topic in שבת Shabbat
when we did מאי חנוכה, Mai Chanukah, the סקוליא, Scolia, the סקוליון
Scholion of מגילת תענית, Megillat Ta'anit, you know there are like two
different branches of the traditions of what those סקוליא scolia are and
the whole sort of גמרא Gemara story about the נס חנוכה nes
Chanukah and going in and finding the שמן shemen etc. had like
an influence on the later versions of those סקוליון Scholion how they
got sort of you know merged and made hybridized and rewritten and
so on. But anyway, we do have these versions of מגילת תענית,
Megillat Ta'anit, both the basic version which is very brief: here's the
date, here's what happened, one sentence or a half a sentence, and
then the sort of later elaboration of it which is written more
in the תלמודי Talmudic and post-תלמודי Talmudic period. So the question
here in the גמרא Gemara whether בטלה מגילת תענית batla Megillat Ta'anit
is is are those days you know does the הלכתי halakhic status
of those days remain? Are you still allowed to not allowed to
fast and eulogize on those days since most of those holidays commemorated
events in the Second Temple period that were connected to the Second
Temple and ones that we certainly don't have any resonance in later
generations? Do those days remain considered minor holidays for this purpose? So
let's take a look.
So it says like this: רב ורבי חנינה אמרי בטלה מגילת תענית.
Rav v'Rabbi Chanina amri batla Megillat Ta'anit. הכי קאמר: Hachi ka'amar: so
now going back to this discussion we had yesterday
about these five fast days and it said these five fast days
were fast days and they will be for rejoicing, so here's how
to read the verse: הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar.
בזמן שיש שלום יהיו לששון ולשמחה: Bizman sheyesh shalom yiheyu l'sasson u'l'simcha:
when there is peace, those things which had been fast days will
turn into days of rejoicing.
אין שלום צום: Ein shalom tzom: and when there is no peace,
fast. no peace, meaning in the time of the חורבן הבית, Churban
habayit, or we said before maybe it even means at a time
of oppression, they'll be fast days. Those are the five fast days
as we know them, והני נמי vahani nami and these days also
mentioned in מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit
כהני ke'hani are just like this. After the חורבן הבית, Churban habayit,
they stop being days of rejoicing and they become no longer have
their status. Now of course it's a little bit ironic, it's a
bad analogy because the five fast days started as fast days. The
point is that paradoxically at time of the at the time of
there is a בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, they somehow become days of
rejoicing. Even that's hard to get your head around, but somehow I
guess you could sort of see that the, you know, that the,
that it's to sort of make a point, you know, these days
had been terrible, they had been tragic or destruction, now we have
sort of shown, you know, we have the last laugh, history has
reversed itself, we now have a בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So somehow,
you know, they become days of rejoicing. Fine, but when there's no
בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, they go back to their natural state. Their
natural state is days of fast because they started as days of
tragedy. Whereas the days in מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit started as days
of rejoicing. So maybe they retain that status even when there's no
בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So it is a very strange analogy, since
when there's no בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash the fast days revert to
being fast, similarly these minor holidays lose their status when there is
no בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. That's the comparison. That's what רב Rav
and רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina say. רבי יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן לוי
אמר, Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi amar, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi disagree, they say
לא בטלה מגילת תענית. lo batla Megillat Ta'anit. No, those fast days
have not ceased having their status. הני הוא דתלינהו רחמנא בבנין בית
המקדש. Hani hu detalia Rachmana bevinyan Beit Hamikdash. It is the, the
fast days that the Torah says when there is a בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash become days of rejoicing, and when not, revert. So their
status as days of rejoicing is explicitly dependent on the presence of
the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. אבל הנך, Aval hanach, the other minor
fast... the other minor holidays, כי דקיימי קיימי, kidekai kai,
their status is not dependent on there being a בית המקדש, Beit
Hamikdash, even when there's no בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash they retain their
status. And again, an easier way to say that is as I
said, these fast days are fundamentally fast days, no בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash they revert. The other days are fundamentally holidays, so even with
no בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash they retain their status as holidays. Okay,
so comparing it to how the five fast days might change their
status is a funny argument, but we have this basic issue of
בטלה מגילת תענית batla Megillat Ta'anit or לא בטלה. lo batla. So
מתיבי רב כהנא, metivei Rav Kahana, we'll get to that, yes we'll
get to חנוכה. Chanukah. מתיבי רב כהנא, Metivei Rav Kahana, רב כהנא
Rav Kahana asks, מעשה וגזרו תענית בחנוכה בלוד, ma'aseh vegezeru ta'anit beChanukah
beLod, in Lod they made,
there was a time where they actually said that there would have
to... there would be a fast on חנוכה. Chanukah. Maybe it was
for rain, maybe it was for some other purpose. So they basically
ignored the fact that מגילת תענית Megillat Ta'anit says, you know, no
fasting on those days, חנוכה Chanukah being one of those days.
וירד רבי אליעזר ורחץ, Veyarad Rabbi Eliezer verachatz, רבי יהושע וסיפר. Rabbi
Yehoshua v'siper. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer went and he bathed and
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua went and he got a haircut and they
basically demonstrated in public that they do not recognize the fast. ואמרו
להם, Ve'amru lahem, and they said to the people who adopted a
fast on חנוכה, Chanukah, צאו והתענו על מה שהתעניתם. tze'u vehit'anu al
mah shehit'anitem. You need to now make a fast to do תשובה
teshuvah for having declared a fast day. Okay, so they basically publicly
rejected their making a fast on חנוכה. Chanukah. So you see לא
בטלה מגילת תענית. lo batla Megillat Ta'anit. Okay now by the way,
you know, before you say, oh חנוכה Chanukah is different, okay, you
know, the point is take a look at תוספות. Tosafot. וירד רבי
אליעזר ורחץ, Veyarad Rabbi Eliezer verachatz, תוספות Tosafot says ממתניתין דאוקימנא ימי
חנוכה לא הוה ליה לאקשויי. m'matnitin de'okaysei yemei Chanukah lo hava lei
le'akshuyei. How about the fact that our משנה Mishnah says that you
still celebrate חנוכה? Chanukah? Isn't that a proof that לא בטלה מגילת
תענית? lo batla Megillat Ta'anit? We still celebrate חנוכה. Chanukah. So תוספות
Tosafot says no, דלעולם לא חשיב יום טוב, d'le'olam lo chashiv yom
tov, ואפילו הכי מדליקין נרות וזכרון הנס. ve'afillu hachi madlikin nerot vezikhron
hanes. תוספות Tosafot says no, you could still have lighting candles, saying
על הנסים, Al Hanissim, and you could still say בטלה מגילת תענית.
batla Megillat Ta'anit. Why? Because maybe you could still have a fast
day on חנוכה. Chanukah. Maybe you could still have a... you know,
have a הספד hesped on מגילת... on חנוכה. Chanukah בטלה מגילת תענית
Batla Megillat Ta'anit is whether that day has a status of a
minor יום טוב yom tov to disallow a fast and a הספד.
hesped. So it does... so we could acknowledge that חנוכה Chanukah, is
still celebrated and still say it has no... בטלה מגילת תענית, batla
Megillat Ta'anit, it has no status from that perspective and you're allowed
to have a fast. So that's what they were doing. All right,
that's what they were doing. They were showing, don't think, you know,
in Lod they thought, yes חנוכה, Chanukah we'll light נרות, nerot, but
we'll have a fast. בטלה מגילת תענית. Batla Megillat Ta'anit. And they
said no, לא בטלה מגילת תענית, lo batla Megillat Ta'anit, you're not
going to be allowed to have a fast day. Okay, but again
it's important to acknowledge that you can, that whether you have חנוכה
Chanukah has a status of a day of הדלקת נרות hadlakat nerot
etc. is independent of the question of its... of בטלה מגילת תענית,
batla Megillat Ta'anit, of whether you're allowed to have a תענית ta'anit
on it or not. Okay, so they went ahead and they demonstrated
this. So אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, so don't you see
that לא lo, בטלה... batlah, that בטלה, batlah excuse me, לא בטלה,
batlah, that you're not allowed to have fast days? אמר רב יוסף,
Amar Rav Yosef, שאני חנוכה דאיכא מצוה. shani Chanukah d'ika mitzvah. חנוכה's
Chanukah different
because But that doesn't mean
that other things will not lose their status. אמר ליה אביי, Amlei
Abaye, so Abaye said to him, ותבטל מצותה? Veseebatel Mitzvaso? Abaye said,
no, let's just wipe חנוכה Chanukah off the books. If we wipe
everything else off the books, why shouldn't we wipe חנוכה Chanukah off
the books? Meaning acknowledging that doing the הדלקת נרות hadlakas neiros is
part of it retaining its status, but as long as we're saying
בטלה מגילת תענית, Batlah Megillat Ta'anis, why shouldn't we wipe the whole
thing off the books? So אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, no,
שאני חנוכה—I'm shani Chanukah sorry, I skipped a line. אלא אמר רב
יוסף שאני חנוכה דמיפרסם ניסא. Ela Amar Rav Yosef shani Chanukah demefarsam
nisa. חנוכה Chanukah, is different because the miracle was very public. Therefore
what? Again, that could just be a reason that it's not just
technically that we do the מצוה, mitzvah, but maybe that it has
particular weight because of the idea of how great the miracle was,
or because of the value of פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, we don't
want to be מבטל mevattel it. If you look at רש"י, Rashi,
רש"י Rashi speaks more
about the societal resistance to change. רש"י Rashi says, כבר הוא גלוי
לכל ישראל על ידי שנהגו בו מצוה והחזיקו בו כשל תורה ולא
נכון לבטלה. Kevar hu galuy lechol Yisrael al yedei shenahagu bo mitzvah
vehiziku bo keshel Torah velo nachon levattla. So רש"י Rashi says, not
because of our desire to do פרסום ניסא, pirsum nisa, or because
of the weight of it and therefore objectively we need to retain
it, it's such an important day, but because it's so entrenched in
society, it's not something that we want to work at reversing. Okay,
so this is very interesting. The question of בטלה לא בטלה מגילת
תענית, Batla lo Batla Megillat Taanit, the first focus is the status
of חנוכה, Chanukah and the question is, can actually we not have
חנוכה Chanukah? at all, or at least if we're going to do
a תענית, ta'anis, allow the תענית ta'anis to override חנוכה? Chanukah? Why
is it and to override the מצוה mitzvah of חנוכה? Chanukah Why
is it that חנוכה Chanukah. retains its status as בטלה מגילת תענית?
Batla Megillat Taanit? And the answer is (a) there's a מצוה mitzvah
and it's ritualized, and (b) it's מיפרסם ניסא, mefarsam nisa, so it's
all this weight and all this entrenchment of חנוכה. Chanukah So חנוכה
Chanukah, is not part of the discussion. Even if בטלה מגילת תענית,
Batla Megillat Taanit, not for חנוכה, Chanukah. and you're not going to
fast on חנוכה. Chanukah Okay, let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Excuse me, it just jogs my memory. I thought there was like
this time that they had a גזירה, gezerah, which was צום גדליה,
Tsom Gedaliah, wasn't one of them? Okay, so you're very good. So
let's keep on reading the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay,
so, all right, so that's the issue. Do the things still have
their status? חנוכה Chanukah clearly does, but that might be that חנוכה
Chanukah, is special. מתיבי רב אחא בר הונא—so Motive lei Rav Achbar
Chuna רב אחא בר הונא Rav Achbar Chuna asks, but here's a
line from מגילת תענית: Megillat Taanit: בתלתא בתשרי בטילת אדכרתא מן שטרייא.
Be-telasa be-Tishrei beteilit adkarata min shtaraya. On the third of תשרי Tishrei
is one of the fast—is one of the minor holidays, because the
God's name or the אזכרה azkarah was taken away, was negated from
the שטרות. shtarot. Now that sounds like a bad thing. But that's
the whole thing. This gives you a feeling of what the text
of מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit is like. Two words for the date,
בתלתא בתשרי, be-telasa be-Tishrei, and four words for explaining what happened, בטילת
אדכרתא מן שטרייא. beteilit adkarata min shtaraya. Okay, the mention of God's
name was taken off of the שטרות. shtarot. So that's the whole
thing. Then afterwards comes the explanation, and this line that we're now
going to read in the גמרא Gemara is part of one of
the אסקולות—the askolos סקוליא scholiot that are on the—that are on the—it
sounds like I'm talking about a Supreme Court justice—oh, that too—anyway, okay,
that's on the מגילה. Megillah. So let's take a look. And now
here's the explanation.
שגזרה מלכות יון גזרה—it's She-gazra malchut Yavan gezerah interesting here, right? The
later text is in Hebrew, but again the earlier one, מגילת תענית,
Megillat Taanit, was in Aramaic, was the vernacular. שגזרה מלכות יון גזרה
שלא להזכיר שם שמים על פיהם. She-gazra malchut Yavan gezerah shelo lehazkir
Shem Shamayim al pihem. That the Greek kingdom,
Hellenistic, thank you, decreed that people cannot mention שם שמים. Shem Shamayim.
You couldn't say God's name.
וכשגברה מלכות חשמונאי ונצחום—and U-keshe-gavra malchut Chashmonai ve-nitzchum a lot of the
dates in מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit are connected to the חשמונאי Hasmonean
period. So when the
חשמונאים Chashmonaim were victorious over the Hellenists or over the Seleucids,
התקינו שיהיו מזכירים שם שמים—they hitkinu she-hayu mazkirim Shem Shamayim decreed that
you should start saying שם שמים Shem Shamayim when you
speak—ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, ברוך השם. Baruch Hashem. ואפילו בשטרות—and Ve-afillu bi-shtarot
even mentioning שם שמים Shem Shamayim in legal documents. וכך היו כותבים—and
Ve-kach hayu kotvim this is what would be written in the legal
documents: בשנת כך וכך ליוחנן כהן גדול לאל עליון. Bishnat kach ve-kach
le-Yochanan Kohen Gadol le-El Elyon. In the year so and so to
יוחנן Yochanan the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to אל עליון. El Elyon.
So they would write לאל עליון le-El Elyon in the documents. וכששמעו
חכמים
בדבר—and U-keshe-shamu chachamim badavar when the sages heard of this, אמרו—they amru
said, למחר זה פורע את חובו—what Limachara zeh poreh et hovo will
happen? They'll write these in normal IOU documents and somebody will pay
up his debt and then he'll be given back the document. And
what will he do with the document? ונמצא שטר מוטל באשפה—he'll Ve-nimtza
shtar mutal be-ashpah throw it in the trash. He'll throw it away,
probably first tear it up and throw it away, ונמצא *v’nimtza* so
you’ll have God’s name in the garbage. וביטלוהו *u’bitlohu* and they said
no more writing God’s names in secular documents. ואותו יום *v’oto yom*
עשו Eisav יום טוב Yom Tov, *asu yom tov* and that day
they made into a יום טוב yom tov. *yom tov* because it’s
not easy to change entrenched practices, certainly not entrenched practices in the
business world. So the fact that they were successful, they made it
into a יום טוב yom tov *yom tov*. Now it's quite interesting
that we have, you know, we do have things from that period,
coins and documents and so on, and absolutely in some of the
coins actually do have say יוחנן כהן גדול *Yochanan Kohen Gadol*, they
don’t, I don't think they say לאל עליון *l'El Elyon*, and nothing
that we have found says לאל עליון *l'El Elyon*. So you know
in any case, you'd say, ah, you see it worked! So
that’s like the old joke, what are you doing? I'm keeping away
zebras. Oh look, it worked! You know, so alright. So anyway, but
there are some interesting questions about like you know about trying to
historically root this type of a thing because it’s because it’s anyway,
there's no evidence that they ever actually did write לאל עליון *l'El
Elyon* in the document. Yes.
Is there any parallels with we having God we trust in every
coin and those things get tossed on the ground?
Alright, there you go, good point. That's right.
And it was they never appeared in coins until the 1950s.
That’s interesting. Joe, what did you want to say? No?
Was there a religious objection to that?
I don't know. Because of that reason? Probably more you got objection
from people, but anyway. So they made the third of תשרי Tishrei.
*Tishrei* a holiday because that was a day where they stopped including
God's name in the documents and that was an important religious event.
Not what I guess the Tosefta I was thinking about was about.
Okay, ואי סלקא דעתך *v’i salka daitach* as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says. Now if you're assuming that בטלה מגילת תענית batla Megillas Taanis
*batla Megillat Taanit*, ואי סלקא דעתך בטלה מגילת תענית Ve-isalkah da'atach batlah
Megillat Taanit, *v’i salka daitach batla Megillat Taanit*, קמייתא בטלה batlah, ואחריתא
מוסיפין *kama’ita batla v’achrita mosifin*? So this is seen as to being
a later תקנה *takanah*, this is at the time of the חשמונאים
Chashmonaim. *Chashmonaim* period. There were ones that were even earlier than that.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that if they were, you know,
נתבטלו *nitbatlu*, you know, you know, negated the earlier ones, why are
they adding? Now of course again, when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* thinks
it was negated, it’s assumed it was negated after חורבן הבית churban
habayit, *Churban HaBayit*. So it's a very funny question because the negation
happens at חורבן הבית churban habayit? *Churban HaBayit*. This the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says גברה מלכות חשמונאי *gavra malchut Chashmonai*, right, but maybe it
seems that גברה מלכות חשמונאי *gavra malchut Chashmonai* is when they started
saying, you know, שם שמים *shem shamayim*, יוחנן כהן גדול *Yochanan Kohen
Gadol*. Some reason the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* thinks that the removing of
the לאל עליון *l’El Elyon* happened much later than the חשמונאים *Chashmonaim*
period. Happened somehow it thinks in the post-חורבן הבית churban habayit. *Churban
HaBayit* period. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says is if they started,
as they eliminated the whole מגילת תענית Megillas Taanis, *Megillat Taanit*, what
are they doing adding dates after the חורבן הבית churban habayit. *Churban
HaBayit*? So it gives an obvious answer. Who said it was after
the חורבן Churban, הבית *Churban HaBayit*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
הכא במאי עסקינן בזמן שבית המקדש קיים *hacha bemai askinan bizman shebeit
hamikdash kayam*. No, they happened when there was a בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*. But now we're going to see why the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* assumed it happened after בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*.
Let's take a look. So says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* top of
י"ט עמוד א' *yud tet amud aleph*, וטיפוק ליה דהוה ליה יום
שנהרג בו גדליה בן אחיקם *v’tipok leh dehavah leh yom sheneherag bo
Gedaliah ben Achikam*. Wait a minute. If it was after, if it
was post-חורבן Churban. הבית *Churban HaBayit*, I understand why you want to
make the third of תשרי Tishrei, *Tishrei* into a holiday because post-חורבן
Churban הבית *Churban HaBayit* what would the third of תשרי Tishrei? *Tishrei*
be? It would be a fast day, it would be צום גדליה
Tzom Gedaliah *Tzom Gedaliah*. So then you’ll have a need to make
it into a holiday. That's why I was assuming this happened after
חורבן Churban. הבית *Churban HaBayit*. You're telling me it happened before חורבן
churban? הבית *Churban HaBayit*. Who needs to make it into a holiday?
צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah? *Tzom Gedaliah* is already a holiday during the
time of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. Because what have
we just said? לששון ולשמחה l'sason v'l'simcha *lesason u’lesimcha*, that during the
time of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash* the fast days
are holidays. So how could this be during the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*? Who needs to turn the third of תשרי Tishrei
*Tishrei* into a holiday? It’s already a holiday because of צום גדליה
Tzom Gedaliah, *Tzom Gedaliah*. You gotta love the irony, it's a holiday,
it's צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah *Tzom Gedaliah* during the time of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*. I keep I told you once
that my brother was once at a חסידיש *Chassidish* שול shul *shul*
on צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah *Tzom Gedaliah* and they didn't say תחנון
*Tachnun* because it was גדליה'ס יארצייט *Gedaliah's Yahrtzeit*.
So anyway, so that’s what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says here. Okay,
it's צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah? *Tzom Gedaliah*, it’s a holiday! Who needs
to make it another holiday? So אמר רב Rav. *amar Rav*, לא
נצרכה אלא לסור שלפניו *lo nitzercha ela lesur shelefanav*. No, by turning
it into a מגילת תענית Megillas Taanis. *Megillat Taanit* holiday, not only
is the day itself forbidden in fasting, but even the day previous
is forbidden in fasting. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* well okay, take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says שלפניו נמי תיפוק ליה
דהוה ליה יום שלאחר ראש חודש chodesh. *shelefanav nami tipok leh dehavah
leh yom shele’achar Rosh Chodesh*, but you could have said ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah*. The day before is the second of תשרי
Tishrei *Tishrei*, that’s a day that follows ראש חודש chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*.
So the same way a holiday impacts the day before, it impacts
the day after. So since you don't fast obviously on ראש חודש
chodesh *Rosh Chodesh* or ראש השנה Rosh Hashana *Rosh Hashanah*, you’re not
going to fast on the second of תשרי Tishrei. *Tishrei* either. So
who needs to give special status to the third of תשרי Tishrei
*Tishrei*? It says no, ראש חודש chodesh, דאורייתא ודאורייתא לא בעי חיזוק
chizuk *Rosh Chodesh d’Oraita v’d’Oraita lo baei chizuk*. The status of ראש
חודש *Rosh Chodesh* as a minor holiday is biblical and therefore we
don't strengthen it and it would not have the impact on the
day after it. So only because it's a rabbinic מגילת תענית Megillas
Taanis, *Megillat Taanit* day on the third of תשרי Tishrei does it
impact the day before, the second of תשרי. Again, assuming it's not
a two-day ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, Braisa, הימים האלה הכתובים במגילת תענית, ha-yamim ha-eileh ha-kesuvim b'Megillas Taanis,
these days that are written in מגילת תענית, Megillas Taanis, אסורים בין
לפניהם בין לאחריהם. asurim bein lifneihem bein l'achareihem.
They make forbidden in fasting, תוספות Tosafos has a long discussion about
whether they also do this for their הספד hesped qualities, but for
their fasting prohibitions, that applies to the days both before and after
things listed in מגילת תענית. Megillas Taanis שבתות וימים טובים הם אסורים
לפניהם ולאחריהם מותרים. Shabbatos v'yamim tovim heim asurim lifneihem v'lachareihem mutarim. But
on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב, yom tov you only can't fast
on the day itself, but before and after you can. מה הפרש
בין זה לזה? mah hefresh bein zeh l'zeh? What is the difference
between one between these two? הללו דברי תורה ודברי תורה לא צריכים
חיזוק. hallalu divrei Torah v'divrei Torah lo tzrichim chizuk. One is biblical
and does not the status of the day and does not need
strengthening, so it's only the day itself. הללו דברי סופרים ודברי סופרים
צריכים חיזוק. hallalu divrei sofrim v'divrei sofrim tzrichim chizuk. The other is
rabbinic and literally סופרים sofrim because it's מגילת תענית, Megillas Taanis it
was actually a very early scroll, right, it was called מגילה Megilla
for a reason, even though it was a period of an oral
tradition, the reason it's so brief and the reason it's in Aramaic
was because it actually was written down and it was a scroll.
So anyway, those need strengthening and it applies to the day before
and the after. Okay,
so now okay, that's presumably later, it's not in terms of it's
a good question how exactly I'd have to I'll have to look
about how when that historically developed. So the גמרא Gemara says, ותיפוק
ליה דהוה ליה יום שלפני יום שנהרג בו גדליה בן אחיקם. v'teipuk
lei d'hava lei yom she-lifnei yom she-neherag bo Gedaliah ben Achikam. The
גמרא Gemara says I still don't get it. You're you said that
this happened during the time of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash We
said when there was a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash who needed to
add it to to to מגילת תענית, Megillas Taanis. it was already
a holiday because it was צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah, which had become
a holiday, and you said to give status to the day before,
but why wasn't there status to the day before on the basis
of the fact that it was צום גדליה? Tzom Gedaliah Same argument.
It was already צום גדליה, Tzom Gedaliah צום גדליה Tzom Gedaliah was
a holiday, that should have had the status of the day before
as well. What do you gain by adding this as a special
מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit holiday?
Can I just ask one thing? Yes. How could it have been
a holiday before the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was destroyed?
Because the פסוק pasuk says that it says לששון ולשמחה l'sason v'l'simcha
when they came to rebuild the second בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. the
people asked should we continue to fast on the fast days, and
זכריה Zechariah said back to them, no, those days that were fast
days will now be days of rejoicing, so now that there is
a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash the five classic fast days that we
have were days of rejoicing. So that's exactly the point, so צום
גדליה Tzom Gedaliah has now become a holiday. So why did you
need to add to create a new holiday on the third of
תשרי, you have the holiday of צום גדליה? Tzom Gedaliah That's after
שיבת ציון.
Shivas Tzion.
Yeah, in time of the second בית המקדש. beit hamikdash.
So
he'd been assassinated and there
at the end of the first בית המקדש beit hamikdash, and now
70 years later, second
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and they're having a סעודה. seudah.
Right.
I mean it's taking לששון ולשמחה very literally, I know it's completely
ironic, but
צום גדליה, Tsom Gedaliah, let's eat.
Exactly. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says this גמרא Gemara is very
funny the way it takes that, it takes that extremely
literally, that how
about it's תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, let's eat. Okay, anyway, the fast
no
longer needing to remember,
I
know, but the fact that it's דווקא davka a holiday, not just
it's a normal day, it's דווקא davka a holiday, right, that's the
גמרא'ס Gemara's point, that's certainly ironic. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ותיפוק ליה דהוה ליה יום שלפני יום שנהרג בו גדליה בן
אחיקם. v'teipuk lei d'hava lei yom she-lifnei yom she-neherag bo Gedaliah ben
Achikam. I don't get it. The whole question was we were saying
that this had to have happened we were questioning how this could
have happened during the time of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash because
it was already צום tzom. גדליה which was already a holiday and
you're telling me that it was to make the day before forbidden
in in תענית, taanis, but same question, if it was already צום
גדליה then the day before should also have been forbidden. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב אשי גדליה בן אחיקם דברי קבלה הוא.
amar Rav Ashi Gedaliah ben Achikam divrei kabbalah hu. No, צום גדליה
is based on פסוקים, psukim, right, and therefore פסוקים psukim in נ"ך,
Nach, דברי קבלה divrei kabbalah means פסוקים psukim in נ"ך, Nach, ודברי
קבלה כדברי תורה דמו v'divrei kabbalah k'divrei Torah damu and that's like
biblical and therefore since it is based on biblical verses, maybe not
תורה Torah verses but verses in נ"ך, Nach, so therefore it would
not make the day before it forbidden. So quite ironic and I
guess צום גדליה becoming a holiday is based on the פסוקים psukim
in זכריה. Zechariah. So here's the point again, why did we have
to make the third of תשרי? The fact that we made the
third of תשרי a minor holiday, the גמרא Gemara assumes that's post-חורבן,
churban. so that shows לא בטלה מגילת תענית, lo batlah Megillas Taanis,
it's still an active idea post-חורבן. churban The גמרא Gemara says no,
it's during the during the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash, During the בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash the third of תשרי is already a holiday because
צום גדליה has become a holiday. And the answer is yes, it's
a holiday but because it's almost like a biblical holiday or quasi-biblical
holiday, it doesn't need the strengthening of the day before, so by
giving it another holiday status of this issue about the שטרות shtaros
and so on, that made it a rabbinic holiday which also had
the impact of the day before. Now you could say that the
very fact that we continue post-חורבן churban to celebrate... To celebrate, to
celebrate, to commemorate צום גדליה, maybe should prove בטלה מגילת תענית batla
Megillas Taanis, because we're not retaining this past holiday of the third
of תשרי. Well anyway, as will come as no surprise because you've
never heard of any of these minor holidays in מגילת תענית Megillat
Taanit other than חנוכה, Chanuka, we do פוסקין pasken בטלה מגילת תענית,
Megillat Taanit okay? But so far we have not yet proved it.
Let's keep on going. Yes.
This is like a huge הלכה halakhic principle here.
כדברי תורה דמו? Kedivrei Torah damu? Right. Yeah, you know, the גמרא
Gemara uses it, uses it at its discretion. Okay, especially here we're
not talking about its real הלכה halakhic weight, we're talking about whether
we feel it needs חיזוק chizuk. or does not need חיזוק. chizuk
So something based on פסוקים... pesukim... Or אסמכתא. asmachta.
No, it's more an issue of אסמכתא. asmachta. חיזוק is a rabbinic
sense about whether people will treat it weightily enough and therefore do
we have to reinforce it. So if it's based on פסוקים pesukim
in the תורה Torah or even פסוקים pesukim in תנ"ך, Tanakh, then
we know people will treat it weightily and we don't feel a
need to reinforce it, right? Whereas whereas things that are purely rabbinic
we might have a greater need to reinforce. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like: מתיבי רב טובי בר מתנא. Masiv Rav Tuvi bar
Masna. So רב טובי בר מתנא Rav Tuvi bar Masna asked, here's
another line from
מגילת תענית. Megillat Taanit, בעשרין ותמניא ביה Be-esrim u-tumnia beih on the
28th in it. So what's in it? No, 28th is, let me
just see if
רש"י... Rashi... באדר קאי במגילת תענית. be-Adar ka'ei be-Megillas Taanis. This is
from the אדר Adar section, okay? So two days before ניסן Nisan
or a day or two before ניסן. Nisan. Okay, so at least
two days. Okay, on the 28th of
אדר, Adar, אתת בשורתא טבתא ליהודאי, asas besorta tava le-Yehuda'ei, a good
report reached the Jews, דלא איעדון מאורייתא, de-la i-idun m-Oraisa, that they
will not have to take themselves away from the תורה. Torah. Again,
so that's the whole story. Six words. They got a report that
they would not have to remove themselves from תורה. Torah. What happened
exactly? So now comes the Hebrew gloss and that explains it. שגזרה
מלכות גזרה, She-gazera malkhus gezera, the, you know, the government made an
edict, שלא יעסקו בתורה, she-lo ya'asku ba-Torah, that they cannot learn תורה.
Torah. We've heard about those edicts before. ושלא ימולו את בניהם, Ve-she-lo
yimolu es beneihem, and they should not do ברית מילה. bris milah.
ושיחללו שבתות, Ve-she-yechalelu Shabbasos, and they should violate שבת. Shabbat. Okay, also
this is assumed to be sort of in the, you know, in
the sort of... well, it's not exactly clear exactly when. Is this
in the Seleucid period? Is this in the Roman period? Okay, let's
take a look. מה עשה יהודה בן שמוע וחבריו? Ma asa Yehuda
ben Shamua ve-chaverav? What did יהודה בן שמוע Yehuda ben Shamua and
his friends do? Now יהודה בן שמוע Yehuda ben Shamua is post
חורבן. churban,
Okay.
Which means end of the... Right. Right, end of the first century.
More and more middle of the second century. Okay, so this is
going to be, so this is going to be during the Roman
period and we know the Romans, right, like the Hadrianic persecutions and
other persecutions had these exact things about not learning תורה, Torah, not
doing ברית מילה, bris milah, and violating שבת. Shabbat. 135. Right. Okay,
הלכו ונטלו עצה ממטרוניתא אחת, halchu ve-natlu eitza mi-matronisa achas, and here's
again a Latin word, מטרון, matron, they went and they took advice
from a מטרוניתא אחת matronisa achas שכל גדולי רומי מצויין אצלה, she-kol
gedolei Romi metzuyin etzlah, that all the important Roman, you know, officers,
government officials are were found by her. Does that does that suggest
that she... Right, so that means that she, yeah, it's not exactly
clear. I don't know, I haven't researched it, but I think that
מטרוניתא matronisa is normally not used in the context of of like
a prostitute or whatever, it's used as a woman of importance social
rank.
Who was bound by her. Yeah.
The way that women were treated in Rome was such that powerful
men would always get to have their way with them.
Even women of important political status, or
who were married to important political men. It is shocking how common
that was.
Really? Okay, so maybe they're both true then. A woman of important
status but it might also mean that men were by her for
political for sexual favors or demands. Okay, so anyway she had a
lot of influence presumably on these men. And they said to her,
"What should we do?" אמרה להם, Amra lahem, she said to them:
בואו והגינו בלילה. Bo vehiginu balaila. Go and do a make a
protest at night. So why exactly night? הפגנה Hafgana מה... why, you
know, why at night? Because at night like the sounds are heard
longer or maybe it's a little bit more impactful to hear...
It's dangerous during the day to demonstrate.
Maybe. You can't see them as well. Maybe. But maybe also maybe
also the sound like, you know, the sense of the power of
the crowd feels greater at night. So they had their own little
Tiananmen Square. So הלכו והגינו בלילה, they went and they protested at
night. אמרו, Amru, and they said: אי שמים, Ei shamayim, which is
like לשם שמים, le-shem shamayim, in the name of heaven. לא אחיכם
אנחנו? Lo acheichem anachnu?
Are we not your brethren? Right, I guess because again עשו is,
you know, brother of יעקב. Yaakov. ולא בני אב אחד אנחנו? Velo
benei av echad anachnu? We have the same father, יעקב? Yaakov? ולא
בני אם אחת אנחנו? Velo benei em achas anachnu? So we have
the same mother, רבקה. Rivka. מה נשתננו מכל אומה ולשון? Ma nishtaninu
mikol umma velashon?
Why have we been treated differently than all other nations שאתם גוזרין...
she-atem gozerin...
So you make these bad, you know, these evil edicts against us
because in general it's true, you know, Rome and the Greeks before
them tended to be pretty tolerant. Of course they were tolerant as
long as you recognized their gods, then you could keep on doing
your own religion. If you were a people that was constantly rebelling
and that you were a people that also refused to recognize their
gods, you know, their toleration might have worn a little bit thin.
But nevertheless, put a statue of your god in their pantheon.
Exactly.
So anyway, okay. וברם Uveram but somehow that was effective; maybe this
woman sort of exerted her influence as well. ואותו היום עשו יום
טוב Ve-oto hayom asu yom tov and that day was a יום
טוב. yom tov. So again it's so funny like the difference of
the days. One day was a יום טוב yom tov. because they
took the name of God out of שטרות. shtarot. And another day
was a יום טוב yom tov because basically there was this terrible
horrific decree from the Roman government which of course was going to
try to basically, you know, drive everybody from religion and no ברית
מילה brit milah and no שבת Shabbat and no תורה Torah and
that got done away with. That's also a יום טוב. yom tov
Okay, anyway like very different significances I would say. Anyway,
alright. So now we have the 28th of אדר Adar was a
יום טוב. yom tov So now let's figure out what we can
infer from this. ואי סלקא דעתך בטלה מגילת תענית, Megillat Taanit and
if מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit. was annulled, קמייתא בטלו ואחייתא מוסיפין? kamaisa
batlu ve-achaisa mosifin? They, if they already stopped at the חורבן churban.
הבית, you know, using it and negated, you know, negated the status
of all those holidays, what are they doing post-חורבן? churban
Because יהודה בן שמוע Yehuda ben Shamoa is post-חורבן. churban. What are
they doing post-חורבן churban. adding to the list? The fact that they're
adding to it post-חורבן churban. shows that it's still active. Now of
course the answer about all of these might be maybe they were
מבטל mevatel מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit, post-חורבן, churban not at the חורבן.
churban But the גמרא Gemara assumes based on these פסוקים pesukim of
יהיו לששון ולשמחה yehiyu lesason ulesimchah that the חורבן churban changes the
status from יום טוב Yom Tov. to non-יום טוב or from יום
טוב to תענית ta'anit that if it was בטלה, it was בטלה
at the חורבן. churban So the גמרא Gemara says you see it's
not בטלה, they're adding days even after the חורבן. churban. So the
גמרא Gemara says וכי תימא, vechi teima, and if you want to
say הכא נמי בזמן שבית המקדש קיים, hacha nami bizman shebeit hamikdash
kayam, if you want to claim this is when there was a
בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash So it can't be, והא יהודה בן שמוע
תלמידו של רבי מאיר, veha Yehuda ben Shamoa talmido shel Rabbi Meir,
יהודה בן שמוע Yehuda ben Shamoa was a student of רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was a student of, you
know, of what do you call it, of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
so that was like in the middle to end of the second
century. רבי מאיר בתר הכי הוה, Rabbi Meir batar hachi hava, and
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was after this. How do you know? תנן,
Tenan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, how do you know that
יהודה בן שמוע Yehuda ben Shamoa was a student of רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, not how you know רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was later,
we know obviously רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was post-חורבן. churban. Okay, תנן,
tenan, כלי זכוכית שניקבו והטיפו לתוכן אבר, klei zechochit shenikvu vehitifu letochan
avar,
you have a glass vessel that has a puncture in it, a
hole in it, and you fill that hole with lead. You know,
you have the whole, you know, that's why there was a lot
of lead poisoning in the ancient days. Okay, so they filled it
with lead, אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
so רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says יהודה בן
שמוע מטמא משום רבי מאיר, Yehuda ben Shamoa metamei mishum Rabbi Meir,
יהודה בן שמוע Yehuda ben Shamoa says it's טמא tamei in the
name of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, וחכמים מטהרין vechachamim mitaherin and the
חכמים chachamim say it's טהור. tahor. So the whole point of bringing
that in was to show you that יהודה בן שמוע Yehuda ben
Shamoa was a student of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, he says something
in the name of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now what does it
mean he was מטמא? metamei? So there's a whole long רש"י Rashi
and תוספות Tosfot trying to figure it out. The simplest answer that
רש"י Rashi has is that כלי klei glass vessels are only מטמא
metamei rabbinically, biblically there's no טומאה tumah on glass vessels, metal vessels
are מטמא metamei biblically. So if you have a glass vessel that's
stopped being functional because it has a hole in it and you
make it functional again by filling it with metal, then it has
a status of a metal vessel and it is biblically טמא, tamei,
whereas the חכמים chachamim say no, it is only a glass vessel.
You know, תוספות Tosfot is bothered that then it wouldn't say חכמים
מטהרין chachamim mitaherin because then all they're really debating is whether it's
biblical or rabbinical. Okay, but nevertheless and there are a couple of
other possible reads of this but we'll stick with that read.
What else is going on in this entire סוגיא? sugia? They're concerned
with whether מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit is a בר סמכא bar samcha
or not?
No, we know that it was always that it was effective for
a long period of time. The question is do the dates remain
in effect and retain their halakhic status after חורבן churban. הבית? Or
do we say that it was בטלה, that a period came and
they said most of these dates connect to historical events at the
time of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash. you know, and that's ancient
history at this point, you know, either it's been overridden because you
know we've got a חורבן churban so that like wipes the slate
clean or it's too much of a distant memory, so they lose
their status.
Oh, so there's a theological implication for framing the time of the
חורבן as so to speak ancient, no longer applicable, the new period.
Okay, that was the way I said it. The גמרא Gemara never
gives the exact reason. I
mean the גמרא Gemara does tie it into this פסוק pasuk of
when there's a שלום shalom then it's ששון ושמחה, sason vesimchah, and
when there's not a שלום, shalom, צום. So yes, presumably in a
post-חורבן period, in a period of גלות, galut, then the joy that
these dates retain loses their power. Right? So you know in the
גלות galut reality, that seems to be the idea behind it. Okay,
but anyway... You see that they were still using it in the
post חורבן period, in the time of יהודה בן טבאי, Yehuda ben
Tabbai, so you see לא בטלו lo batlu because they were still
using it. So the גמרא Gemara says תנאי, tannai, it's a debate
of תנאים tannaim whether it was still in use post חורבן. דתניא,
Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braita: הימים האלו הכתובים במגילת תענית,
Hayomim ha'elu haktuvim beMegillat Taanit, the days listed in מגילת תענית, Megillat
Taanit, בין בזמן שבית המקדש קיים ובין בזמן שאין בית המקדש קיים
אסורין, bein bizman sheBeit Hamikdash kayom uvein bizman she'ein Beit Hamikdash kayom
asurin, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. So very interesting, רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says they retained their status and they're even after the
חורבן הבית. Now it works, יהודה בן שמוע Yehuda ben Shamua was
a student of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. It works out beautifully. So
רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's student was adding to those days because רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir now said that, you know, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
was the one that said, well actually יהודה בן שמוע Yehuda ben
Shamua didn't add. The story was in the time of יהודה בן
שמוע, Yehuda ben Shamua, he was one of the people that were
part of, you know, that effected the change in the Roman government's
edict. But anyway, it so it works well. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says the מגילת תענית Megillat Taanit retains its status even post חורבן.
רבי יוסי אומר בזמן שבית המקדש קיים אסורין מפני ששמחה היא להם.
Rabbi Yose omer bizman sheBeit Hamikdash kayom asurin mipnei shesimcha hi lahem.
When they're, and here you get down to the theological statement, no,
when there's a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash those days retain their status
because they are days of joy. אין בית המקדש קיים מותרין מפני
שאבל הוא להם. Ein Beit Hamikdash kayom mutarin mipnei she'avel hu lahem.
When there's no בית המקדש they become permissible to have fast days
and to eulogize
because it is a day of mourning. So this is an interesting
reversal, right? The same way the days of mourning became days of
joy, the five fast days in the time of the second בית
המקדש, here we're not just saying these days of joy stopped being
days of joy post חורבן. We're actually going to the opposite extreme:
what used to be days of
joy now become days of mourning, in a way that's easier to
understand than the reversal, right? How you take תשעה באב Tisha B'Av
which is a day where tragedy, the tragedy of the בית המקדש
or tragedy of the people, lives were lost, how you turn that
into a day of rejoicing just because now it's time of the
בית המקדש is hard to understand. But the reverse is less hard
to understand. This was a day of joy because it, you know,
because everything was going so well in those days. Now that we're
living in a גלות galut exile, you know, bleak period, to think
about those times actually maybe increases the sense of angst, right? We're
remembering how great things used to be and now, from our perspective,
that increases the degree of loss. So again, quite interesting the way
it's going from one extreme to the other. But the basic point
is not that you actually now start fasting on those days but
they do not have their status as minor יום טוב. So the
גמרא Gemara says והלכתא ve'hilchata and the הלכה halacha is בטלו, batlu,
those days are nullified now in the חורבן reality. Those days do
not have any הלכתי halachic status. והלכתא Ve'hilchata and the הלכה halacha
is לא בטלו, lo batlu, they did not lose their status. So
the גמרא Gemara says קשיא הלכתא אהלכתא, kashya hilchata ahilchata, we have
a problem of two traditions of what the הלכה halacha is. לא
קשיא, Lo kashya, כאן בחנוכה ופורים כאן בשאר יומי. kan baChanuka u'Purim
kan b'sha'ar yomei. We've already indicated חנוכה, Chanuka now we throw in
פורים. Purim. חנוכה Chanuka and פורים Purim are days that have lasting
significance, maybe because they were entrenched as the, as the גמרא Gemara
said earlier, they were so entrenched within society, maybe because of the
פרסומי ניסא, pirsumei nisa, the weight of the significance of those days,
the fact that they were connected to מצוות. mitzvot. But those are
days that did not get reversed. But every other day got reversed
once there was a חורבן הבית. Yes, Charlie.
Today, twenty-seven אייר, Iyar, is a day that is listed in מגילת
תענית.
Excellent, for what purpose?
We stopped paying tribute to the Greeks in the time of the
חשמונאים.
Very nice, great.
I had meant to bring in the whole scholarly edition of מגילת
תענית, amazing.
Maybe I will, I'll bring it in when we learn the סוגיא
sugya because it's a very, the סוגיא sugya of מגילת תענית gets
repeated in מסכת תענית. Masechet Taanit. Okay, now let's continue.
All right, but yeah,
I find this is, it's astounding that this entire discussion
culminates with חנוכה Chanuka. and פורים. Purim. I mean, פורים Purim has
a biblical book. It's an entire biblical book. Right. In other words,
you might think that they would say that's why פורים Purim gets
retained.
Right, well the גמרא Gemara never actually had to justify פורים Purim
gets retained, it only had to justify חנוכה. So you might be
right, meaning it could just be that פורים Purim obviously is retained,
it's not based on מגילת תענית, it's based on a biblical book.
You could very well be right. Okay, so now so we're moving
on in the משנה. Mishnah. So the first thing we focused on,
which got us onto this discussion, is why are they going out
for תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and not going out for שבעה עשר
בתמוז Shiva Asar B'Tammuz or עשרה בטבת. Asara B'Tevet.
And that led to a whole discussion that the minor fast days
since they don't always apply and so on, the שלוחים shluchim did
not go out for. And that gets us a whole מגילת תענית
about minor fast days, minor holidays and so on. Back to the
משנה. Mishnah. על אלול מפני ראש השנה. Al Elul mipnei Rosh Hashana.
And שלוחים shluchim would go out on אלול Elul in order that
people could figure out when ראש השנה Rosh Hashana, is, assuming אלול
Elul would only be twenty-nine days, okay? Because obviously you can't go
out ראש השנה for ראש השנה, it's too late. ועל תשרי מפני
תקנת המועדות. Ve'al Tishrei mipnei takanat hamo'adot. And they'd go out again
on תשרי to tell people when תשרי was established even though people
were assuming it was established on day thirty of אלול, Elul, but
they would go out again just to reinforce that or reinforce that.
to, you know, to make it certain that that was the day
that it was established. Okay, as a backup. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says כי נפקי דאלול אתשרי למה להו *ki nafkei de'Elul a
Tishrei l'ama lehu*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks the question, I
don't get it. You went out on אלול *Elul* because you could
assume אלול *Elul* is only going to be twenty-nine days. Why do
you have to go out again on תשרי *Tishrei*? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says וכי תימא דיעברוה לאלול *vechi teima d'ibruha l'Elul* because
maybe it's not a hundred percent. It's possible that אלול *Elul* would
be thirty days. So you wanted to go out on תשרי *Tishrei*
just to be certain. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר רבי
Rabbi. חנינא בר כהנא אמר רב מימות עזרא ואילך *amar Rabbi Chanina
bar Kahana amar Rav mimot Ezra v'eilach* but one minute. We say
that from the time of עזרא *Ezra* onward לא מצינו אלול מעובר
*lo matzinu Elul me'ubar* אלול *Elul* has never been thirty days. Now
by the way תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says why we say from the
time of עזרא *Ezra* because if you look closely in the פסוקים
*pesukim* of עזרא *Ezra* and you read them it it sounds like
אלול *Elul* was thirty days at that time from certain stories there.
But anyway, so why would you have to go out again on
ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*? We could assume אלול *Elul* was twenty-nine days.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no. לא מצינו דלא איצטריך *lo
matzinu d'lo itztarich*. We never found because it was never necessary. הא
איצטריך *ha itztarich*, it doesn't mean it's impossible. It's happened that way
so far. If it was necessary מעברינן ליה *m'abrinan leh*, we would
do an we would make it thirty days. Now what's the איצטריך
*itztarich*? So רש"י Rashi. *Rashi* says it has to do with the
fact that like, you know, when we want יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
to fall out on, we don't want יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* and
שבת *Shabbat* to be back to back. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says you
know, no, that's like because that's not תיקון מועדות *tikkun moadot* in
the plural. And anyway תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* basically says it just means
if the witnesses came late, not איצטריך *itztarich* because of manipulating calendar
reasons. It means if the circumstances warranted because the witnesses didn't come
on the thirtieth day.
If the witnesses didn't get right.
We'd make it thirty days. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one
minute. הא מיקלקל ראש השנה *ha mikalkal Rosh Hashanah*. One minute. If
you're going to make אלול *Elul* thirty days, you're going to ruin
ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*. Now why are you going to ruin ראש
השנה *Rosh Hashanah*? You're going to ruin ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* because
everybody is celebrating ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* on day thirty. Everybody is
assuming אלול *Elul* is twenty-nine days. What you should do, this is
the way תוספות Tosafot... *Tosafot* reads the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, sort of
like one of those תקנות *takanot* of the time of רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי *Rabban Yochanan ben Zakai* about when you accept witnesses, is
you should refuse to accept witnesses on day thirty, you know, that
it was a thirty-day אלול *Elul*. You should always just make it
a twenty-nine day אלול *Elul* regardless of what the witnesses say. Because
if you allow for the possibility of a thirty-day אלול *Elul*, you'll
ruin ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*. People will celebrate ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*
assuming it was day twenty-nine and you're now going to make it,
you know, assuming אלול *Elul* was twenty-nine days and you're now going
to make אלול *Elul* thirty days.
And you have like a ראיה *re'iyah* of some sort of an
astronomical ראיה *re'iyah*.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, you know, but then there's
this issue which we'll get to which is okay but בית דין
Beit Din *Beit Din* can always do whatever they want in the
end and they can ignore that.
Even if they're wrong. Okay, well that's the way תוספות *Tosafot* is
reading it. You know, you shouldn't allow it. You should insist that
אלול *Elul* be twenty-nine days. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no.
מוטב תתקלקל ראש השנה ולא יתקלקלו כולהו מועדות *mutav titkalkal Rosh Hashanah
v'lo yitkalkelu kulhu moadot*. Better that ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* should be
ruined, not really ruined, but people sort of wound up celebrating the
wrong day because they were assuming that אלול *Elul* was twenty-nine days,
but we shouldn't ruin the other מועדות *moadot*, meaning the מועדות *moadot*
should be made in the right time based on when the moon
appears and we're not going to just to, you know, not make
it difficult for people, we're not going to not accept the testimony
on the new moon. So therefore although it has not yet happened
that אלול *Elul* has been thirty days, it might happen. We're going
to allow for that possibility, we'not going to disallow it, and therefore
we need to send out שלוחים shluchim *shluchim* on תשרי *Tishrei* because
it is always possible it was a thirty-day אלול *Elul*, not a
twenty-nine day אלול *Elul*. Okay. So the גמרא *Gemara* says דיקא נמי
דקתני על תשרי מפני תיקון המועדות *deika nami deka tani al Tishrei
mipnei tikkun hamoadot*. So yes, that in- that can be inferred, this
idea that we will accept witnesses for ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* תשרי
*Tishrei*, you know, up through day, you know, even to allow a
thirty-day אלול *Elul*. Because it says the witnesses would go out to
fix the מועדות *moadot*. דיקא נמי דשמע מינה *deika nami deshama mina*.
That's a good point, which shows that the idea is תיקון *tikkun*,
fixing the מועדות *moadot*, means that the מועדות *moadot* are linked and
that ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* is linked to the actual time the
moon appears, which means that the מועדות *moadot* are occurring in their
right time based on the actual appearance of the moon. And therefore
it is always possible that it was not a twenty-nine day אלול
*Elul*, it was a thirty-day אלול *Elul*. So we send out the
שלוחים shluchim *shluchim* again even though it's been very, very rare, we
have to allow for that possibility.
Even that language is interestingly ambiguous because it could mean the opposite.
תיקון מועדות *tikkun moadot* could mean the בית דין *Beit Din*.
Like the manipulation of it. Yeah, could be. Okay, ועל כסלו מפני
חנוכה ועל אדר Adar מפני פורים Purim. *ve'al Kislev mipnei Chanukah ve'al
Adar mipnei Purim*. We just mentioned before חנוכה *Chanukah* and פורים Purim
*Purim* as the two surviving holidays from the pre- חורבן *Churban* period,
the rabbinic holidays from the pre- חורבן *Churban* period, and those get
and those we continue and we send out שלוחים shluchim *shluchim* so
people know when to celebrate. חנוכה *Chanukah* was the one they had
the most advance warning for. So the גמרא *Gemara* says ואילו נתעברה
השנה יוצאים אף על אדר שני Adar Sheni מפני פורים Purim לא
קתני *ve'ilu nitabra hashanah yotzim af al Adar sheni mipnei Purim lo
katani*. One minute, you know what the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* didn't say?
You- the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* is listing all the possibilities like it
says when there's a בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* they go out for
פסח Pesach. שני Sheni. *Pesach Sheni*, so it should have mentioned another
possibility. What's the other possibility? That if it was... was a עיבור
year, if it was a leap year, then the fact that they
sent out witnesses on the first אדר Adar, wouldn't have been enough;
they'd have to send out witnesses on the second אדר, Adar because
the second אדר Adar... is when you celebrate פורים. Purim. So that
didn't say that in the משנה. Mishnah Why not? מתניתין דלא כרבי.
Matnitin d'lo k'Rabbi.
It's not like רבי. Rabbi, דתניא Detanya we taught in a ברייתא,
Beraita, רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, if it was a leap year, יוצאין
אף על אדר שני מפני הפורים. yotzin af al Adar Sheni mipnei
ha-Purim. You'd go out on אדר שני Adar Sheni. for פורים Purim
because פורים Purim is going to be celebrated in אדר שני. Adar
Sheni. You already went out on אדר ראשון Adar Rishon but now
it's too late so you have to go out again on אדר
שני. Adar Sheni.
And people are observing in אדר ראשון, Adar Rishon,
they go out on אדר שני.
Adar Sheni Right, but that doesn't count according to רבי, Rabbi so
you have to go out again on the שני. So the גמרא
is now going to
ask... they'd have to do a second פורים. Purim Yeah, they'd have
to do a second פורים Purim? and even if they celebrated the
first one. So that's clearly what רבי Rabbi holds. So now the
גמרא's going to try to figure out well why did our משנה
Mishnah not mention it and essentially you'll say what you're implicitly saying.
So the גמרא says, לימא בהא קמיפלגי. Leima be'ha kamiflagi. Let's say
this is the debate. דמר סבר, De'mar savar, כל מצות הנוהגות בשני
נוהגות
בראשון, kol mitzvot ha-noahgot be-sheni nohagot be-rishon, and also our משנה holds
all the מצות mitzvot that apply in אדר שני Adar Sheni. apply
in אדר ראשון, Adar Rishon, which doesn't just mean like you gotta
do it twice, which actually could mean that if you did it
in אדר ראשון Adar Rishon you were יוצא. yotze. So maybe our
משנה holds you were יוצא yotze in אדר ראשון, Adar Rishon, so
they wouldn't bother going out for אדר שני. Adar Sheni. ומר סבר,
U-mar savar, כל מצות הנוהגות בשני אינן נוהגות בראשון. kol mitzvot ha-noahgot
be-sheni einan nohagot be-rishon. And רבי holds no, the מצות mitzvot even
if you assumed, even if you did it in אדר ראשון Adar
Rishon it doesn't count, they only can be done in אדר שני.
Adar Sheni. And therefore you need to go out again for אדר
שני. Adar Sheni? So that's the debate whether you would need to
celebrate פורים Purim again. Now תוספות asks a question. תוספות says, I
don't get it, even if you don't have to celebrate פורים Purim?
again, you gotta send out שלוחים shluchim if you made a leap
year. Why do you have to send out שלוחים shluchim if you
made a leap year after everybody celebrated פורים? Purim Forget that you're
not going to have to do a פורים Purim? again. Why do
I need to know you made a leap year?
Because it's going to be starting to prepare for פסח. Pesach?
When is פסח? Pesach I need to know you made a leap
year so I know not to make פסח Pesach next month. So
תוספות says yeah, but that you'll figure out because you never heard
of because the שלוחים shluchim from ניסן Nisan never arrived. So the
absence of the שלוחים shluchim of
ניסן Nisan will be an indication they made it as a leap
year, which is still pretty funny. You don't want people's basic celebration
of פסח Pesach, to be so indeterminate. Okay, but somehow that's what
the גמרא's saying. If the גמרא is ignoring the fact that you
need to know it was a leap year in order to figure
out פסח, Pesach. that's somehow you'll figure out and the only, maybe
that message gets across, oh בית דין made a leap year. That
you hear. Exactly which day did they make אדר ראשון Adar Rishon
and אדר שני? Adar Sheni 30 days or 29 days, maybe that
you... anyway that's not bothering the גמרא how you know it's a
leap year and there won't be a פסח. But the גמרא says
is why don't you have to know it's an
אדר שני Adar Sheni to do פורים? Purim, And maybe the debate
is whether you were יוצא yotze פורים Purim, with אדר ראשון. Adar
Rishon. So let's take a look. So the גמרא says לא, not
necessarily. דכולי עלמא, De-kulei alma, מצות הנוהגות בשני אינן נוהגות בראשון. mitzvot
ha-noahgot be-sheni einan nohagot be-rishon.
We could say everybody agrees that what you did in אדר ראשון
Adar Rishon didn't count. So if it didn't count, why don't you
have to go out for אדר שני Adar Sheni. so people know
when to celebrate פורים? Purim. והכא בעיבור שנה קמיפלגי. Ve-hacha be-ibbur shana
kamiflagi.
The debate is about
how much you would add when you made an עיבור שנה. ibbur
shana. What does that mean? דתניא Detanya we learned in a ברייתא,
Beraita, כמה עיבור שנה? kama ibbur shana? How much would you add
for the עיבור שנה? ibbur shana? ל' יום, Lamed yom, it would
always be a 30 day.
Okay, so
just let me glance in תוספות... in רש"י. No. So excuse me,
right. How much would אדר... Adar it's a little funny because conceptually
you're adding אדר שני. Adar Sheni But since אדר שני Adar Sheni
has the status of the real אדר Adar because אדר שני Adar
Sheni is when you celebrate פורים, what winds up being the case
is which year do you get to conceptualize as the leap month?
Which month is אדר ראשון? Adar Rishon? Right, it's a little bit
ironic. Conceptually you're adding an extra אדר Adar before ניסן Nisan comes
about. But since that second אדר Adar, gets the status of the
real אדר, Adar the leap month conceptually אדר ראשון. Adar Rishon. Okay,
so this is the question of how long is אדר ראשון? Adar
Rishon? How many days is the leap month that you are going
to add? Maybe it's fixed, maybe it's just as indeterminate as every
other month on the moon. Let's take a look. כמה עיבור שנה?
Kama ibbur shana? How much how big is that month that you've
added? ל' יום. Lamed yom. Always 30 days. Once you're adjusting the
calendar might as well maximally adjust it and make it 30 days.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, חודש. A
month. Which means yes, but presumably a month in contrast to 30
days means 29 days.
So the גמרא says... so anyway, so the גמרא says that's the
debate. So the point is we don't have to send out שלוחים
shluchim for אדר שני Adar sheini because again presumably people will know
that it was a leap year. How we can assume that people
will know it's a leap year is not clear. Okay, that they'll
get word of. So the only reason we'd need שלוחים shluchim would
be to, they want to know the precise day. Was did the
second אדר Adar. start on day 30 or on day 31? So
the גמרא says maybe that's the debate. One opinion says that it
will always start on day 31.
אדר ראשון Adar Rishon would... so it's also a fixed amount. So
the גמרא says where were we? Did they make announcements in שול
like it's a
I don't know. So the גמרא says like this, so, so the
גמרא says מאי שנא ל' דיידיע. mai shena lamed deyadiah. So you
say that if it was 30 days, they didn't need to send
שלוחים shluchim? because they would have known that the אדר ראשון Adar
rishon was 30 days, they would have known when אדר שני Adar
sheini began. וחודש נמי ידיע. vechodesh nami yedia. So if חודש means
29 days, they also would have known when אדר שני Adar sheini
began. We're back to square one. Why do you need שלוחים shluchim
for אדר שני Adar sheini? assuming people know that it's a leap
year? So the גמרא says אמר רב פפא amar Rav Pappa מן
דאמר חודש. man de'amar chodesh. No, חודש does not mean 29 days.
If you say חודש, it means רצה חודש רצה שלשים. ratza chodesh
ratza shloshim. It could be 29 or 30, it's a there's no
fixed size for אדר ראשון. Adar rishon. So what does the גמרא
say now? The גמרא has said that would you send out שלוחים
shluchim for אדר שני? Adar sheini It could be everybody agrees you
need to know אדר שני Adar sheini in order to make פורים,
but would you send out שלוחים? shluchim. So the גמרא's assuming that
everybody also knows whether it's a leap year. So the debate whether
you send out שלוחים shluchim is just a debate of do can
you can you without the שלוחים shluchim figure out when אדר שני
Adar sheini begins, assuming you know it was a leap year. So
if you say it's always a fixed size of אדר ראשון Adar
rishon 30 days, then you don't need the שלוחים. shluchim You know
it's a leap year, you'll know when אדר שני Adar sheini begins.
It begins on the 31st of אדר ראשון, Adar rishon, the day
after day 30. If you say, however, the size of אדר ראשון
Adar rishon varies, then you're going to need שלוחים shluchim even if
you know it's a leap year because you still need to know
exactly what day אדר שני Adar sheini began so that you can
properly celebrate פורים. Okay, so now the גמרא continues.
Okay. אמהיב ר' יהושע בן לוי משום קהלא קדישא דירושלים. Amhiv Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi mishum kehala kadisha d'Yerushalayim. We've had that a couple
of times. קהלא קדישא דבירושלים. Kehala kadisha d'viYerushalayim. I have no idea.
The holy community of Jerusalem. על שני אדרים. Al shenei Adarim. When
you have two אדרס Adars שמקדשין אותם ביום עיבוריהן shemikadshin otam beyom
ibureihen that you sanctify them on the day of their pregnancy, meaning
day 30. So that the אדר ראשון Adar rishon is 29 days
and אדר שני Adar sheini is 29 days. The new moon begins
on the pregnant day, the extra day, on day 30. So both
אדרס Adars are 29 days. So the גמרא says למימרא. lemeimra. This
says דחסירן עבידן מלאן לא עבידן dechassiran avidan male'an lo avidan that
we only do
29-day אדרס, Adars, not 30 days. Before we had an opinion that
דוקא davka we do 30 days. Here it's saying we דוקא davka
do 29 days. So the גמרא says לאפוקי מדרש רב נחמן בר
חסדא. la'apukei midrash Rav Nachman bar Chisda. But this is an opinion
that's a third opinion. One opinion said אדר ראשון Adar rishon could
be 29 or 30, one said always 30. This opinion says not
only אדר ראשון Adar rishon but אדר ראשון Adar rishon and אדר
שני Adar sheini only 29. And that is to reject the position
of רב נחמן בר חסדא. Rav Nachman bar Chisda. If you look
at the side of it, it's the words דדרש רב נחמן בר
חסדא. dedarash Rav Nachman bar Chisda. רב נחמן בר חסדא Rav Nachman
bar Chisda explicated העיד ר' סימאי משום חגי זכריה ומלאכי. He'id Rabbi
Simai mishum Chaggai Zecharya uMalachi. ר' סימאי Rabbi Simai testified quite fascinatingly
in the name of the three נביאים nevi'im חגי זכריה ומלאכי Chaggai
Zecharya uMalachi that were there in the in the building of the
second בית המקדש. So there's a few years between those two. Anyway,
between חגי זכריה ומלאכי Chaggai Zecharya uMalachi and רב סימאי. Rav Simai.
Anyway, he testified a tradition going back all the way to them
על שני אדרים al shenei Adarim on two אדרס Adars שרצו לעשות
שניהם מלאים עושים. sheratzu la'asot sheneihem mele'im osim. You can make them
both full. שניהם חסרים עושים. sheneihem chaseirim osim. You can make them
both 29 days. אחד מלא ואחד חסר עושים. echad malei ve'echad chaser
osim. You could make one full and one חסר. chaser. Okay, you
could do whatever you want. Okay, so as opposed to now we
have a range of opinions. One says it always varies, one says
it's always 29 days, the other says it's always 30 days. Okay.
וכך היו נוהגים בגולה. Vechach hayu nohagim baGola. And that was the
practice that they used to do in the exile before they returned
to the second בית המקדש to have a lot of variation in
terms of the size of the אדר. ומשום רבינו אמרו. Umishum Rabbeinu
amru. In the name of our master they said. Okay,
that's רב. לעולם אחד מלא ואחד חסר. Le'olam echad malei ve'echad chaser.
It's always one full and one lacking in that order. Meaning אדר
ראשון Adar rishon is always 30 days, אדר שני Adar sheini is
always
29 עד שיודע לך שקבעו ראש חודש בזמנו. ad sheyivadei lach shekave'u
Rosh Chodesh bizmano. Unless you have an explicit testimony that the that
the אדר שני Adar sheini was in its time. In its time
always means the previous month was a 29-day month. So we basically
assume a 30-day אדר ראשון Adar rishon a 29-day אדר שני Adar
sheini unless you have concrete knowledge that they made the אדר ראשון
Adar rishon a 29-day. Okay, so you're going to be tested on
all these opinions later. The upshot of course being that there's a
whole range of opinions whether אדר ראשון Adar rishon has to be
29 days, has to be 30 days, or is a variant. Okay.
Anyway, but again, do you need שלוחים shluchim. to go out for
אדר שני Adar sheini assuming that people we can assume that people
know it's a leap year? Do whether you need שלוחים or not
for אדר שני Adar sheini. depends on whether you can al- have
a if אדר ראשון Adar rishon is always a fixed number of
days you don't need שלוחים for אדר שני. If it's a variant
number of days you do need שלוחים. Let's look at one more
line. Look at that, we caught up. So שלחו ליה למר עוקבא.
shalechu lei lemar Ukva. They sent to מר עוקבא mar Ukva the
following question: אדר הסמוך לניסן Adar hasamuch leNissan And not the question,
actually the statement that they sent a message that if it's the
אדר *Adar* that is near ניסן *Nissan*, meaning if it's אדר שני
*Adar Sheni* or if it's not a leap year, but the אדר
*Adar* immediately preceding ניסן *Nissan* is always 29 days, which fits into
that statement in the name of רב *Rav* that it's 30 and
29; the one before ניסן *Nissan* is always 29 days. Okay, so
now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: מתיב רב נחמן *Masiv Rav
Nachman*. So רב נחמן *Rav Nachman* asks on this: על שני חדשים
מחללין את השבת *Al shenei chadashim mechalelin es ha-Shabbos*, you would violate
שבת *Shabbos* to come testify, and we're going to see this later
that the witnesses could break שבת *Shabbos* to come to the בית
המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* to testify about two months: על ניסן ועל תשרי
*Al Nissan ve-al Tishrei*, on ניסן *Nissan* and תשרי *Tishrei*, because those
are the months that you really had to establish in the right
time because those would determine when the ימים טובים *Yomim Tovim* would
be.
With what? With חילול *Chiluul* תחום *Techum*?
Yeah, or if you had to just yeah, תחום *Techum* or carrying
if you had to carry an old person who saw it and
couldn't do the walking himself. Okay, so you could actually biblically violate
שבת *Shabbos* to come and testify on the new moon on those
two months. We'll see that, it's later in our משנה *Mishnah*. אי
אמרת בשלמא זימנין מלא וזימנין חסר משום הכי מחללין *I amarta bishlama
zimnin malei zimnin chaser mishum hachi mechalelin*, I get if אדר *Adar*
before ניסן *Nissan* could vary, so you have to violate because you
don't know how long אדר *Adar* is going to be and you
need to establish it in its right time. Okay, because obviously if
you're coming for ניסן *Nissan*, it means that you are testifying that's
when אדר *Adar*, the אדר *Adar* ends and ניסן *Nissan* begins. So
if the אדר *Adar* always ends on a fixed number of days,
on 29 days, why would you be able to violate שבת *Shabbos*?
You know when ניסן *Nissan* is going to begin. אלא אי אמרת
*Ella i amarta* כ עמוד א *chaf amud aleph*, if you said
לעולם חסר *l-olam chaser* that אדר *Adar* is always 29 days, so
you know without the witnesses when ניסן *Nissan* will begin. So אמאי
מחללין *amai mechalelin*? Why would you violate? So גמרא *Gemara* says: No,
משום דמצוה לקדש על הראיה *mishum de-mitzvah lekadesh al ha-re'iyah*, that even
if you know what day it's going to be and even if
somehow you've manipulated it that it's going to be that day, there's
a מצוה *mitzvah* to do it based on testimony and that מצוה
*mitzvah*, even if the calendar is not dependent on it, that מצוה
*mitzvah* would tell you you can violate שבת *Shabbos*. We'll just read
one other version of that. איכא דאמרי *Ika de-amrei*, some say: אמר
רב נחמן אף אנן נמי תנינא *Amar Rav Nachman af anan nami
tenina*, we also taught, על שני חדשים מחללין את השבת על ניסן
ועל תשרי *Al shenei chadashim mechalelin es ha-Shabbos al Nissan ve-al Tishrei*.
אי אמרת *I amarta*, so now it's going to be used the
opposite way: if you say בשלמא לעולם חסר *bishlama l-olam chaser*, אדר
*Adar* is always 29 days, משום הכי מחללין *mishum hachi mechalelin*, then
I get why you violate שבת *Shabbos* for ניסן *Nissan*. That's a
little ironic. Why? Because you're already assuming the answer: משום דמצוה לקדש
על הראיה *de-mitzvah lekadesh al ha-re'iyah*, because there's a מצוה *mitzvah* to
do it based on the testimony and that would be enough even
though we know when the date would be. אלא אי אמרת זימנין
מלא וזימנין חסר *Ella i amarta zimnin malei zimnin chaser*, but if
you don't know whether it's going to be 29 or 30 days,
okay, אמאי מחללין *amai mechalelin*? Why would you violate? נעבריה להאידנא *Na-abreih
l-ha-idna*, why don't we just assume it's going to be a 30-day
month ונקדשיה למחר *u-nekadsheih le-machar* and sanctify the following day? Okay, so
exactly what that means, oh I forgot it's Tuesday so we really
have to end. Okay, so we will see tomorrow why the גמרא
*Gemara* assumes that you can use that evidence to prove the exact
opposite. Okay, so we'll pick up with that tomorrow whether אדר *Adar*
is always 29 days or whether.